Overview of the J. Arthur and Edna Mouw papers
Hoover Institution Archives
J. Arthur and Edna Mouw papers
1931-2004
2008C2
Mouw, J. Arthur, 1903-
1 manuscript box, digital files (0.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Photocopies of letters, sound recordings of reminiscences, pamphlets, and studies, relating to missionary work among the Dayak people of Borneo. Includes a printed memoir by Sydwell Mouw Flynn, daughter of J. Arthur and Edna Mouw.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Use copies of all sound recordings in this collection are available. For access to any video recordings or motion picture film in this collection, please contact the Hoover Institution Archives.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2008.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
American missionary in Borneo, 1931-1950.
Scope and Content of Collection
Photocopies of letters, sound recordings of reminiscences, pamphlets, and studies, relating to missionary work among the Dayak people of Borneo. Includes a printed memoir by Sydwell Mouw Flynn, daughter of J. Arthur and Edna Mouw.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Dayak (Indonesian people)--Missions.; Missions--Indonesia.; Missions--Borneo.; Missionaries.; Mouw, Edna, 1901-; Flynn, Sydwell Mouw, 1933-
Partial Collection Contents
- Sound Recordings, 1958-1972
  - J. Arthur Mouw sermon: Making His Deeds Known, undated
    Use copy reference number: 2008c2_a_0000961
    Mouw begins discussing his ministry history on the Borneo island, including his friendship with another missionary. His main focus is a tale about a merchant that lives near the river and their prayer for rain, the message being when God helps one person, God is helping many people. Mouw also discusses another man named Jon.
  - J. Arthur Mouw sermon: The Gospel Multiplied, 1972 September 20
    Use copy reference number: 2008c2_a_0000962
  - J. Arthur Mouw sermon: All Power Has Been Given, undated
    Use copy reference number: 2008c2_a_0000963
    A talk on his missionary service to Borneo. Includes a good deal on marriage in Borneo and a tale about curing a man of the hiccups.
  - J. Arthur Mouw sermon: Beautiful Feet, 1971 September 22
    Use copy reference number: 2008c2_a_0000964
    Mouw recalls a tale in Borneo of wishing to travel to one village as he had promised, but being kept by another village interested in his ministry. Includes stories of the taste of Borneo fruit, falling asleep from exhaustion during a teaching session, and baptizing.
  - J. Arthur Mouw sermon at the Men's Fellowship North Redona Chapel, undated
    Use copy reference number: 2008c2_a_0000965
    Mouw recalling leaving the South Pacific during WWII, going through Australia, Panama, New Orleans, and finally into California. Following, he talks about the Gospel and the Dayaks and other tribes of Borneo, particularly the man with a goatee.
  - J. Arthur Mouw sermon on his work in Borneo, undated
    Use copy reference number: 2008c2_a_0000966
    A talk on his missionary work in Borneo, beginning in 1931 and teaching people to sing. Mouw spends some time preaching from Old Testament stories. He goes on to discuss the Borneo natives pre-Christianity prayer and non-prayer traditions, growing up and prayer with his father, handshaking, and the seriousness of baptizing.
  - J. Arthur Mouw sermon: Djapit, The Cook, undated
    Use copy reference number: 2008c2_a_0000967
    A sermon on missionary work in Borneo. Includes his wife leaving the Dayaks, a tale of a tribe member dying, and building a church.
  - J. Arthur Mouw sermon: A Decision Reversed, 1958 November 7
    Use copy reference number: 2008c2_a_0000968
    Mouw discusses his interactions with the Dutch officials in regards to his work with the Dayaks. He discusses major breakthroughs coming from speaking Dutch fluently and rationally explaining the health benefits for the Dayaks from Mouws ministry.
  - J. Arthur Mouw sermon: The Escape Story, 1972 September 24
    Use copy reference number: 2008c2_a_0000969
    Mouw discusses his experience in Borneo following the Pearl Harbor bombing in the beginning of the US-Japan front of WWII. Mouw vividly recalls the path and trials his family took from Borneo, passing through Australia, New Zealand, Panama before arriving home in Pasadena, California. Concludes with the hymn "Throw A Line". Cassette sounds very bad and did not respond to restoration treatments
  - J. Arthur Mouw sermon: An Example of God's Faithfulness, undated
    Use copy reference number: 2008c2_a_0000970
  - J. Arthur Mouw sermon: A Story From Borneo, undated
    Use copy reference number: 2008c2_a_0000971
    A talk by Mouw to young people describing what he calls persecution he received from the Dutch officials in Borneo and persecution the tribes suffered from their chiefs. He likens this persecution to events in the Bible and events the young people might encounter. Includes a tale about a young Dayaks religious act being confused for an act of political revolution.
  - J. Arthur Mouw sermon: Safety Pins, undated
    Use copy reference number: 2008c2_a_0000972
    A talk on interaction and trade with Dayaks.
  - J. Arthur Mouw sermon: Moving Day In Borneo, 1972
    Use copy reference number: 2008c2_a_0000973
    A talk on baptizing Dayaks, housing, bringing his wife up from the city, and the concept of being born again. In the process he recalls how the Dayaks turned to Christianity, and the Dayak women had vetoed turning to Islam.
  - J. Arthur Mouw sermon: Matter of Blood, undated
    Use copy reference number: 2008c2_a_0000974
    A talk on the difference between Natives customs versus the born again Dayak customs. Concerns the "Business of the Blood," animal slaughter.